A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Office Files of Enid C.B. Schoettle FA604
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, United States International Affairs Program (USIAP), Office Files of Enid C.B. Schoettle
1976-1991
Rockefeller Archive Center
Schoettle, Enid C. B., 1939-
Ford Foundation
FA604
6.65 Cubic Feet 17 Hollinger boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011.
The initial transfer of Enid C.B. Schoettle Office Files was ingested by the RAC as a part of Accession 2012:040. Later sets of Schoettle's Office Files were transferred to the RAC in 2019 and ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2019:031 and 2019:056.
Accessions continue as necessary.
Scope and Contents
Collection contains the office files of Ford Foundation program executive Enid C.B. (Curtis Bok) Schoettle. From 1976 to 1993, Schoettle occupied a number of positions in the Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP), a unit that was once organized under the Foundation's United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP). Schoettle served as Program Officer, Program Officer in Charge, and Director of IAP. Her work primarily focused on managing grants for international security and arms control research and initiatives.
Three types of files are found within the collection: 1) Meeting and trip files; 2) Subject files; and 3) Chronological correspondence files. Each of the different file types are organized and described in an individual series within the collection. The contents of these series document the progression of the Ford Foundation's grant funding priorities from the mid-1970s to the early 1990s within the field of international security. Correspondence, memos, grant proposals, and Recommended Grant Action records (RGAs) show the Foundation's support of research competitions for university-based research and training centers in international security and arms control, fellowships in international security and arms control and Soviet Union/Eastern European studies, and research and trainings focused on specific subjects related to international security. Major institutional recipients of these international peace related grants include the Brookings Institution, the Rand Corporation, the International Institute for Security Studies (IISS), and a number of universities like the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, the University of California Los Angeles, and Indiana University. Within the collection, researchers will also find records that regard other aspects of the International Affairs Program's work that Schoettle supported such as grant funding for an internship program at Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE-RL), international economics research and projects, and the strengthening of European integration through assistance to the Centre for European Policy Studies (CEPS). The administrative tasks Schoettle took on as she gained more responsibilities in IAP are documented as well.
Common material formats found within the collection that have not been previously mentioned include papers, itineraries, publications, drafts, and invoices.
The collection consists of more than one accession of Enid C.B. Schoettle office files. Later sets of records transferred to and ingested by the Rockefeller Archive Center in 2019 (Accession 2019:031 and 2019:056) shared the same file types as the original material and were therefore integrated into the established collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Arrangement
Collection consists of 3 series that are based on file type: Meetings and trip files; Subject files; and Chronological correspondence.
A later accession of records containing Enid C.B. Schoettle's meetings files was added to where the original material ended in Series 2. Later accessions of records containing Schoettle's chronological correspondence was placed in Series 3 according to the files' date of origin in order to restore the chronological system of arrangement the records' creators intended.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Meetings, 1979-1991
Series 2. Subject files, 1977-1991, bulk 1987-1991
Series 3. Chronological correspondence, 1976-1987
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas.
During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Biographical / Historical
Enid C.B. (Curtis Bok) Schoettle (1939-2018) was an educator, foundation program executive, and leader in nuclear disarmament and international relations scholarship. She worked for almost two decades in the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP) as a Program Officer, Program Officer in Charge, and Director. Most of her work at Ford focused on managing grants related to international security and arms control research and initiatives.
Schoettle graduated with a BA in History from Radcliffe College in 1960 and then received a Ph.D. in Political Science from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1967. Before joining the Ford Foundation in 1976, she taught Political Science at the University of Minnesota.
In 1981, Schoettle was promoted from Program Officer to Program Officer in Charge of the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program. Her position then changed to Director in 1987. She left the Foundation in 1993.
Following her career at Ford, Schoettle joined the U.S. Government's National Intelligence Council as National Intelligence Officer for Global and Multilateral Affairs. She then occupied the position of Chief of the Advocacy and External Relations Unit of the United Nations Department on Humanitarian Affairs. In 1998, she became Consultant and Special Advisor to the Chairman of the National Intelligence Council. Schoettle retired from public work in 2004.
In addition to her work at the Ford Foundation, the United Nations, and the National Intelligence Council, Schoettle served as a member of a variety of organizations such as the Council on Foreign Relations and the Advisory Board of Women in International Security. She joined the Board of Directors for the Henry L. Stimson Center after her retirement. In 1996, Schoettle was recognized for her work on the National Intelligence Council by being awarded the National Intelligence Distinguished Service Medal.
Ford Foundation; Arms control; Europe; Europe, Eastern; International agencies; International economic relations; International organization; International relations; Nuclear energy -- Government policy; Security, International; Soviet Union
- Meetings, 1979-1991; 1; 2.56 Cubic Feet About 4.25 LTR and 2 LGL size Hollinger boxes
  Scope and Contents
  Series contains the meeting and trip files Enid C.B. Schoettle created during her time in the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP). These records primarily originate from the mid-1980s to the early 1990s. They regard Ford Foundation program meetings, meetings Schoettle and the International Affairs Program organized for specific guests or topics, meetings organized by Foundation grant recipients like the International Institute for Security Studies (IISS), site visits to grant recipients or potential grant recipients, country visits, and other meetings, conferences, and workshops related to international security and arms control.
  The series also holds a list of Grants and Projects out of Appropriation for October 1, 1965 to December 31, 1965. The list has a note, dated May 21, 1979, from a Joseph W. Currie on the front. The relationship between the list and Enid C.B. Schoettle's meeting and trip files is unclear. Perhaps, the list was placed in the original box that contained the meeting files by mistake.
  The series consists of more than one accession of records transferred to the RAC from the Ford Foundation. A second set of meeting and trip files was added to the end of the series.
  - Sir Crispin Tickell Lunch, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Luncheon for Permanent Representatives to the United Nations, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters received regarding Luncheon for Permanent Representatives to the United Nations, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Affairs Program (IAP) Meeting - Cairo, Egypt/Israel Trip, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Council on the United Nations System (ACUNS) Third Annual Meeting, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Meeting on "The Gulf Crisis: The Security Council and the Future", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Meeting on Foundations in East/Central Europe - Letters of Invitation, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Meeting on Foundations in East/Central Europe - Background material/submitted drafts, etc., 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Meeting on Foundations in East/Central Europe - Materials distributed at meeting, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Meeting on Foundations in East/Central Europe - Reports, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) Silver Jubilee Annual Conference: The Conduct of East-West Relations in the 1980s, Ottawa, Canada, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Trip to Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty (RFE-RL), Munich, Germany, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
  - East Europe trip, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Brazil, Argentina, and Chile trip, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - United States Information Agency (USIA) - Fulbright 40th Anniversary Washington D.C. Conference, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Inter-University Seminar on Armed Forces and Society, Chicago, Illinois, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Canadian Centre for Arms Control and Disarmament trip, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Palme Commission Meeting, New Delhi, India, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 24-26)
  - Arms Control Association (ACA)/International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) "New Faces" Conference, Castelgandolfo, Italy, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Miscellaneous note from Stanley J. Heginbotham, 1989 January 9 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Grants and Projects out of Appropriation, Fiscal Year 1966, October-December, 1965, 1979 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 29-30)
  - London, England trip, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Soviet Union trip, 1985-1987 (Box 4, Folder 32-34)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) - Polish conference, Warsaw, Poland, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Aspen Institute Berlin Conference on Rethinking the Role of Conventional Forces and Arms Control in European Society, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Institute for East-West Security Studies (IEWSS) Conference on the Impact of Technology on the Future of European Security and Cooperation, Helsinki, Finland, 1986-1987 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Nuclear History Project (NHP) conference, Munich, Germany, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies - United States-Soviet Relations Conference: Eastern Europe, Lucerne, Switzerland, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Germany travel guide and International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) visit, London, England, 1986-1987 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) Annual Conference, Barcelona, Spain, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Third Special Session of the United Nations General Assembly Devoted to Disarmament, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology - Schoettle visit with Franklin A. Thomas, 1985-1989 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Stockholm International Peace Research Institute (SIPRI) conference, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Soviet Union and Hungary trip, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Aspen Institute Berlin Conference: Where Is Germany Heading?, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - The American Council on Germany (ACG) and Atlantik-Bruecke - American-German Biennial Conference, Dearborn, Michigan, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Georgetown University trip, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - United States Information Agency (USIA) - Cultural and Educational Agreement between the United States and Spain, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Third Annual Conference of Social Science Research Council (SSRC)-MacArthur Foundation Fellows in International Peace and Security, Morelos, Mexico, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 50-51)
  - Cambodia and the United Nations meeting, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - National Research Council conference - Status and Prospects of Soviet Social Science: The Challenge for the American Scholarly Community, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) Annual Conference, Oslo, Norway, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - International Peace Academy (IPA) Workshop on The United Nations and International Security: United States, Soviet, and Third World Perceptions of Regional Conflict Management, Briarcliff Manor, New York, 1988-1989 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace Conference on Nuclear Non-Proliferation: The Role of Private Organizations, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Joint Meeting between the United Nations Association of the United States of America (UN-USA) and the Soviet-UN Association, 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 57-58)
  - National Conference on the United States and the United Nations, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - International Institute for Strategic Studies (IISS) Heads of Institutes Meeting, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - Poland trip, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Ford Foundation Conference on Czechoslovakia, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 62-64)
  - White House Symposium for Non-Profit Organizations on Assistance to Eastern Europe, 1989-1990 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Poland and Hungary trip, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 66)
- Subject files, 1977-1991, bulk 1987-1991; 2; .48 Cubic Feet About 1.25 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains the subject files Enid C.B. Schoettle created during her time in the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP). These records chiefly originate from Schoettle's time as IAP Director and regard IAP program reviews. The series also holds a few chronological correspondence files for consultants with whom Schoettle worked such as Johan Holst. These chronological files are not like the extensive files found in Series 3 for Schoettle's correspondence. They each only include one or a few pieces of correspondence.
  - Goodwin, Craufurd - Chronological file, 1987 November (Box 7, Folder 67)
  - Holst, Johan - Chronological file, 1990 May (Box 7, Folder 68)
  - International Peace, Security, and Arms Control (IPSAC) Competition - Recommended Grant Actions (RGAs) and other important documents, 1977-1991 (Box 7, Folder 69-73)
  - Leven, Bozena - Chronological file, 1987 September 24 (Box 7, Folder 74)
  - Program Review - United States and International Affairs Program (USIAP) 1988 Fiscal Year, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 75)
  - Program Review - Mini Program Review Presentation, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 76)
  - Program Review - International Affairs Program (IAP)/Developing Countries Program (DCP) 1989 Fiscal Year, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 77)
  - Program Review - International Affairs Program (IAP) 1990 Fiscal Year, 1989-1990 (Box 8, Folder 78-79)
  - Program Review - International Affairs Program (IAP) 1990 Fiscal Year (Box 8, Folder 80)
  - Work/Family Task Force, 1987-1989 (Box 8, Folder 81)
- Chronological correspondence, 1976-1987; 3; 3.61 Cubic Feet About 9.5 LTR size Hollinger boxes
  Series contains the chronological correspondence files Enid C.B. Schoettle created during her time in the Ford Foundation's International Affairs Program (IAP). The correspondence in these files chiefly regard grant proposals, grant evaluations, research competitions for grant funding, meetings, trips, conferences, program reviews, and administrative matters. Within these letters, Schoettle communicated with other IAP staff members, executives and employees in the larger Ford Foundation, grantees and potential grantees, consultants, and other academics and policy experts within the field of international security and arms control.
  The series consists of more than one accession of records transferred to the RAC from the Ford Foundation. A second set of chronological files was integrated into the series based on the dates from which the material originated in order to restore the chronological system of arrangement the records' creators intended. Schoettle's correspondence from between 1979 and 1980 and from 1988 until her retirement are still missing from the series. Future accessions of material may add the files to the collection.
  - Chronological file, 1976 September (Box 8, Folder 82)
  - Chronological file, 1976 October (Box 8, Folder 83)
  - Chronological file, 1976 November (Box 8, Folder 84)
  - Chronological file, 1976 December (Box 8, Folder 85)
  - Chronological file, 1977 January (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Chronological file, 1977 February (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - Chronological file, 1977 March (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Chronological file, 1977 April (Box 9, Folder 89)
  - Chronological file, 1977 May (Box 9, Folder 90)
  - Chronological file, 1977 June (Box 9, Folder 91)
  - Chronological file, 1977 July (Box 9, Folder 92)
  - Chronological file, 1977 August (Box 9, Folder 93)
  - Chronological file, 1977 September (Box 9, Folder 94)
  - Chronological file, 1977 October (Box 9, Folder 95)
  - Chronological file, 1977 November (Box 9, Folder 96)
  - Chronological file, 1977 December (Box 9, Folder 97)
  - Chronological file, 1978 January (Box 9, Folder 98)
  - Chronological file, 1978 February (Box 9, Folder 99)
  - Chronological file, 1977-1978 (Box 9, Folder 100)
  - Chronological file, 1978 April (Box 10, Folder 101-102)
  - Chronological file, 1978 April-May (Box 10, Folder 103)
  - Chronological file, 1978 June (Box 10, Folder 104)
  - Chronological file, 1978 July (Box 10, Folder 105)
  - Chronological file, 1978 July-August (Box 10, Folder 106)
  - Chronological file, 1978 September (Box 10, Folder 107)
  - Chronological file, 1978 October (Box 10, Folder 108)
  - Chronological file, 1978 November (Box 10, Folder 109)
  - Chronological file, 1978 December (Box 11, Folder 110)
  - Chronological file, 1981 July (Box 11, Folder 111)
  - Chronological file, 1981 August (Box 11, Folder 112)
  - Chronological file, 1981 September (Box 11, Folder 113)
  - Chronological file, 1981 October (Box 11, Folder 114)
  - Chronological file, 1981 November (Box 11, Folder 115)
  - Chronological file, 1981 November-December (Box 11, Folder 116)
  - Chronological file, 1982 January (Box 11, Folder 117)
  - Chronological file, 1982 February (Box 11, Folder 118)
  - Chronological file, 1982 March (Box 11, Folder 119)
  - Chronological file, 1982 April (Box 11, Folder 120)
  - Chronological file, 1982 April-May (Box 11, Folder 121)
  - Chronological file, 1982 April-June (Box 12, Folder 122)
  - Chronological file, 1982 July (Box 12, Folder 123)
  - Chronological file, 1982 August (Box 12, Folder 124)
  - Chronological file, 1982 June-September (Box 12, Folder 125)
  - Chronological file, 1982 October (Box 12, Folder 126)
  - Chronological file, 1982 November (Box 12, Folder 127)
  - Chronological file, 1982 December (Box 12, Folder 128)
  - Chronological file, 1983 January (Box 12, Folder 129)
  - Chronological file, 1983 February (Box 12, Folder 130)
  - Chronological file, 1983 February-March (Box 12, Folder 131)
  - Chronological file, 1983 April (Box 12, Folder 132)
  - Chronological file, 1983 May (Box 12, Folder 133)
  - Chronological file, 1983 June (Box 12, Folder 134)
  - Chronological file, 1983 July (Box 12, Folder 135)
  - Chronological file, 1983 August (Box 13, Folder 136)
  - Chronological file, 1983 September (Box 13, Folder 137)
  - Chronological file, 1983 October (Box 13, Folder 138)
  - Chronological file, 1983 November (Box 13, Folder 139)
  - Chronological file, 1983 December (Box 13, Folder 140)
  - Chronological file, 1983-1984 (Box 13, Folder 141)
  - Chronological file, 1984 February (Box 13, Folder 142)
  - Chronological file, 1984 March (Box 13, Folder 143)
  - Chronological file, 1984 April (Box 13, Folder 144)
  - Chronological file, 1984 May (Box 13, Folder 145)
  - Chronological file, 1984 June (Box 13, Folder 146)
  - Chronological file, 1984 July (Box 13, Folder 147)
  - Chronological file, 1984 August (Box 13, Folder 148)
  - Chronological file, 1981-1984 (Box 13, Folder 149)
  - Chronological file, 1984 October (Box 13, Folder 150)
  - Chronological file, 1984 July-November (Box 14, Folder 151)
  - Chronological file, 1984 November-December (Box 14, Folder 152)
  - Chronological file, 1984-1985 (Box 14, Folder 153)
  - Chronological file, 1985 January-February (Box 14, Folder 154)
  - Chronological file, 1985 February-March (Box 14, Folder 155)
  - Chronological file, 1985 March-April (Box 14, Folder 156)
  - Chronological file, 1985 May (Box 14, Folder 157)
  - Chronological file, 1985 June (Box 14, Folder 158)
  - Chronological file, 1985 July (Box 14, Folder 159)
  - Chronological file, 1985 April-August (Box 14, Folder 160)
  - Chronological file, 1985 August-September (Box 14, Folder 161)
  - Chronological file, 1985 August-October (Box 14, Folder 162)
  - Chronological file, 1985 September-November (Box 15, Folder 163)
  - Chronological file, 1985 November-December (Box 15, Folder 164)
  - Chronological file, 1986 January (Box 15, Folder 165)
  - Chronological file, 1986 January-February (Box 15, Folder 166)
  - Chronological file, 1986 January-March (Box 15, Folder 167)
  - Chronological file, 1986 April (Box 15, Folder 168)
  - Chronological file, 1986 March-May (Box 15, Folder 169)
  - Chronological file, 1986 June (Box 15, Folder 170)
  - Chronological file, 1986 July (Box 15, Folder 171)
  - Chronological file, 1986 August (Box 16, Folder 172)
  - Chronological file, 1985-1986 (Box 16, Folder 173)
  - Chronological file, 1986 October (Box 16, Folder 174)
  - Chronological file, 1986 November (Box 16, Folder 175)
  - Chronological file, 1986 December (Box 16, Folder 176)
  - Chronological file, 1986-1987 (Box 16, Folder 177)
  - Chronological file, 1987 February (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Chronological file, 1987 March (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Chronological file, 1987 April (Box 16, Folder 180)
  - Chronological file, 1987 March-May (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Chronological file, 1987 May-June (Box 17, Folder 182)
  - Chronological file, 1987 July (Box 17, Folder 183)
  - Chronological file, 1987 June-August (Box 17, Folder 184)
  - Chronological file, 1987 September (Box 17, Folder 185)
  - Chronological file, 1987 October (Box 17, Folder 186)
  - Chronological file, 1986-1987 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Chronological file, 1987 December (Box 17, Folder 188)